<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The god-father's advice to his son shewing the necessity of performing the baptismal vow and the danger of neglecting it : with general instructions to young persons to lead a religious life and prepare them for their confirmation and worthy receiving of the blessed sacrament : very necessary for parents, &amp;c. to give their children or others committed to their care / by John Birket ...</title>
            <author>Birket, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28214</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16106</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12255900</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12255900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57468</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28214)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57468)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 203:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The god-father's advice to his son shewing the necessity of performing the baptismal vow and the danger of neglecting it : with general instructions to young persons to lead a religious life and prepare them for their confirmation and worthy receiving of the blessed sacrament : very necessary for parents, &amp;c. to give their children or others committed to their care / by John Birket ...</title>
                  <author>Birket, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition,</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Knapton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 44.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Anglican Communion.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57468:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57468:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE God-father's Advice TO HIS SON.</p>
            <p>Shewing the Neceſſity of performing the BAPTISMAL VOW, AND The Danger of Neglecting it.</p>
            <p>WITH General Inſtructions to young perſons to lead a Religious life, and prepare them for their Confirmation, and worthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Bleſſed Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Very neceſſary for Parents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to give their Children, or others committed to their care.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Birket,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Milford</hi> and <hi>Hordle</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Edition, with a Preface.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Knapton,</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1700.</p>
            <p>Price Three-pence. One 100 for 1 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57468:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:57468:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my Loving Friends and Pariſhioner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> THE INHABITANTS OF</hi> Milford <hi>and</hi> Hordle, <hi>In the County of</hi> Southampton.</head>
            <p>ALtho I chiefly compoſed this ſmall Treatiſe for the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of thoſe, in whoſe names (upon the requeſt of their Parents) I covenanted with God at their Baptiſm; yet being ſenſible how neceſſary the practice of the ſame Advice, may be for all others committed to my charge; I have therefore taken care that the youth of other Families in both my Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhet, may have the ſame to peruſe at their leiſure.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I am ſenſible how backward moſt perſons are in their younger years, to read, underſtand, and practice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that may be for the Souls health, without a great deal of care and diligence in thoſe with whom they live; therefore it is my earneſt requeſt to all of you, who are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parents, Maſters, or any otherwiſe concerned in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of youth, to be often putting them in mind of thoſe things which are contained herein. And whereas your own good examples through the Bleſſing of God will be moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailable to beget in them a due ſenſe of their Duty, and render this advice the more effectual, let me therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you alſo to take care that the practice of your own lives be conformable unto it.</p>
            <p>For it is not eaſie to ſuppoſe that this ſmall treatiſe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l have its due influence upon the minds of the younger ſort, while you that are the Elders ſhall behave your ſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary thereunto.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57468:3"/>
            <p> But conſider, I beſeech you, what a joyful and pleaſant thing it will be when once we can be ſo happy as to be perfectly united in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgment, in reference to theſe things; making it our Buſineſs to glorify God by a chearful obſervance of our Baptiſmal vow, by duly ſanctifying the Lords Day, and by behaving our ſelves with all Decency and Reverence, with all Fervency and Zeal, when we draw nigh unto God in thoſe places which are ſet a part for his publick Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Do you think it would not be a more lovely ſight, and more pleaſing to God as well as Man, to behold a whole Congregation offering up their Supplications and Prayers to God, with an humility both of Soul and Body, and proſtrating themſelves before the Throne of Grace, with a pure heart and humble voice, accompanying the Miniſter in the ſeveral parts of Divine Service as the Church directs, and to have every one with a audiable voice, heartily ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> at the end of ever Prayer, to teſtify his conſent and Faith. Would not this be a more lovely ſight, I ſay, than to have the greateſt part of a Congregation in different poſtures, ſome standing, others ſitting, a few kneeling, and many never ſo much as once opening their Lips, that their mouths may ſhew forth Gods praiſe.</p>
            <p>You cannot be ignorant with what frequency and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I have both privately and publickly recommended theſe things to your conſideration, and thanks be to God there is ſomething more of Decency and Reverence to be ſeen, than there was formerly; but yet there is a great deal ſtill to be amended; and in order to this end, I have put this little Book into your hands, which if you will be ſo kind as to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe and practice, I doubt not but you will thereby come to glorify God, and edify one another more than many of you have hitherto done; which, that you may do, is the hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your aſſured Friend, and Loving Paſtor,</hi> Jo. Birket.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57468:3"/>
            <head>The God father's Advice to his Son.</head>
            <p>WHereas I have, together with ſome others, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the requeſt of your Parents, undertaken the office of a Surety for you at your Baptiſm; at which time it was given us in charge to ſee that you ſhould be taught, ſo ſoon as you ſhould be able to learn, what a ſolemn vow, promiſe and profeſſion you then made by us: I have endeavoured accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to diſcharge my duty thus far, and have alſo advis'd you with all due reverence to frequent the publick worſhip of God, giving diligent attention to the miniſtry of his holy word and to prayer.</p>
            <p>Whereas it was then alſo given us in charge to take care that you ſhould be brought to the Biſhop to be confirmed by him, ſo ſoon as you ſhould be duly qualify'd for the ſame, I have advis'd you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to take the firſt opportunity of obſerving that holy ordinance.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it is very probable that you may not ſo well remember what you have ſome time heard, as what you ſhall often read, therefore I have thought fit to compoſe this ſmall Treatiſe for your uſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I have taken in hand,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To explain your Baptiſmal Vow, which in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation you are requir'd to take upon yourſelf, ſhewing you withal the poſſibility of keeping it, and the obligation which you are under to obſerve it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſhew you in what manner you ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have yourſelf in the publick worſhip of God, that ſo your whole ſervice and your ſelf alſo may be accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, through the merits of his beloved Son.</p>
            <p>And this I am the rather inclin'd to do at preſent, leſt you ſhould be led away with the error of thoſe people, who boldly now adays exclaim againſt theſe things, to the very great decay of Chriſtian piety, and the ſcandal of thoſe who are truly religious.</p>
            <p>For, ſay they, what man living is able to keep this vow; and from hence they conclude, that it's a vain
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57468:4"/> and ſinful thing for any one to make it in another's name.</p>
            <p>Again, ſay they, what need is there of ſo much exactneſs in our bodily geſtures in Gods publick worſhip, ſince he expects to be worſhipp'd by us in ſpirit and in truth.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſo plauſible objections, that the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Chriſtians are prejudic'd againſt theſe things; and hence it comes to paſs, that as in moſt Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations there is ſo much irreverence to be ſeen in time of divine ſervice, ſo in moſt places there are ſo few that are willing to undertake the office of Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for Children at their Baptiſm, fewer that make thoſe anſwers in the Childs name which they ſhould do with an audible voice, and fewer yet who make any conſcience of diſcharging their duty afterwards, but come to the Font as if they had nothing elſe to do but to ſtand ſilent there, tho afterwards they can loudly contribute to all the fooliſh mirth among their neighbours.</p>
            <p>And therefore I ſhall now proceed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. of all to explain the Baptiſmal Vow.</item>
               <item>2. To prove unto you the poſſibility of keeping it.</item>
               <item>3. To ſhew you how great an Obligation you lye under to obſerve it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Therefore whereas you promiſed by us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Devil, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you muſt know, that by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing any thing is meant a declaring againſt it, or a forſaking it, and reſolving to have no more to do with it, a refuſing to comply with it, or to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by it.</p>
            <p>And thus our Church has explain'd the word in the firſt interrogatory to the Sureties. For, ſays the Miniſter unto them, <hi>Doſt thou in the name of this Child renounce the Divil and all his works, the vain pomp and glory of the world, with all covetous deſires of the ſame, and the carnal deſires of the fleſh, ſo that thou wilt not follow nor be led by them?</hi> To which they are required to make anſwer and ſay, I renounce them all. By which is meant, that whoſoever Covenants with God to be his faithful Servant, does thereby oblige
<pb facs="tcp:57468:4"/> himſelf not to be at Satans beck, nor led by the vain cuſtoms of the world, or the luſts of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>And in this ſenſe we find the word <hi>renounce</hi> us'd by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Ep. to Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>ch.</hi> 2. where ſpeaking in vindication of himſelf, he declares that he had not been ſlothful in the work of the Miniſtry, but had <hi>renounced</hi> the hidden things of diſhoneſty, <hi>i. e.</hi> he diſdained to have any thing to do with thoſe baſe Arts and cunning Tricks, which ſome others made uſe of in handling the word of God.</p>
            <p>So that in promiſing <hi>to renounce the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh,</hi> you declared by us, that you would op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all their temptations, and no way comply with them to the diſhonour of God, and the deſtruction of your Soul.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas you promiſed alſo by us to believe all thoſe fundamental Doctrines of Chriſtianity, which are briefly comprehended in that form of ſound words which is called the Apoſtles Creed, I cannot ſuppoſe that there is any neceſſity for explaining that part of your Baptiſmal Vow in this ſmall Treatiſe, becauſe as there are no great difficulties in it, ſo there are no great diſputes about it, it being generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Chriſtian Church by men of all perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, how different ſoever from one another in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other points.</p>
            <p>However, this one thing I cannot omit letting you know, <hi>viz.</hi> that you are ſo to believe all theſe Articles, as to take care that the practice of your life and converſation be anſwerable to all thoſe things which you profeſs to believe.</p>
            <p>That is to ſay, you muſt ſo believe in God as to dread his almighty power and greatneſs, and yet adore and love him for his immenſe mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. You muſt ſo believe in Jeſus Chriſt as to walk according to thoſe excellent rules of his holy Goſpel which he has given us; and you muſt ſo believe in the Holy Ghoſt, as not to grieve him by following any vicious or idle courſes; and thus in reference to all the other Articles of our Chriſtian Faith, you muſt ſo reflect upon them as to be admoniſhed thereby of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57468:5"/> your duty, and effectually moved to the performance of it. And now</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wheteas you promiſed alſo by us <hi>to keep Gods holy will and commandments, and to walk in the ſame all the days of your life,</hi> it is requiſite that I give you a more large explication of this part of the Baptiſmal vow, becauſe there are ſo many and ſo great miſtakes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Chriſtians about it.</p>
            <p>You muſt know therefore that you are not hereby to underſtand a perfect and unſinning obedience, for it is utterly impoſſible for any man to live, without being guily of diſobedience to God upon many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts; but by keeping the Commandments of God now under the Goſpel is meant our uſing the moſt ſincere endeavours to do thoſe things which God has required, being unfeignedly ſorrowful for all our frailties and imperfections, heartily begging Gods pardon through Chriſt for what we have done amiſs, and conſcientiouſly putting our holy reſolutions of new obedience into practice, ſtill exerciſing our faith, and relying upon Gods mercies in Chriſt Jeſus to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us.</p>
            <p>So that in acknowledging our ſelves bound to keep Gods holy will and commandments, and to walk in the ſame all the days of our life, we do not in the leaſt mean that our good works are meritorious, or that we can be ſav'd purely through any the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent works of righteouſneſs which we can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, but our obedience to the Goſpel is required, as the beſt teſtimony of the ſincerity of our faith.</p>
            <p>And hence it is that our Saviour is ſaid <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>to be the author of eternal Salvation to all that obey him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let no man therefore deceive you, by extolling faith to the diſparagement of good works; for as St. <hi>John</hi> has told us, 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 5. 3. that <hi>our keeping the commandments of God is the beſt evidence of our love to him,</hi> ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> has taught us, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>that we are Gods workmanſhip, created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works, that we ſhould walk in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner St <hi>Peter,</hi> 2 <hi>Ep.</hi> 1. 5, 6. tells us we muſt not think it ſufficient <hi>that we are made partakers of</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57468:5"/> 
               <hi>the Divine nature, having eſcaped the corruption that is in the world through luſt; but</hi> (ſays he) <hi>beſides this, giving all diligence, add to your faith vertue, and to vertue, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for if theſe things be in you and abound they make you that ye ſhall be neither barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And thus (my Son) having ſhew'd you the true meaning of your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Vow, I ſhall in the ſecond place prove unto you the poſſibility of keeping it.</p>
            <p>And for this, I ſuppoſe, there needs no better proof than Gods requiring theſe things of us in order to our Salvation, and his ſetting before us the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of holy men in Scripture for our encouragement, and imitation of them in this matter.</p>
            <p>For ſo infinitely juſt and merciful is our heavenly father, that he expects no more from us than he knows we are able to perform, through the gracious aſſiſtance of his holy ſpirit, concurring with our own ſincere endeavours.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place therefore, as to our renouncing the Devil, has he not commanded us by his Apoſtle St <hi>James,</hi> ch. 4. 7. <hi>to reſtſt</hi> him, promiſing withal, that thereupon he ſhall <hi>flee from us.</hi> Has he not enjoin'd us alſo by his Apoſtle St <hi>Paul,</hi> Eph. 4. 27. <hi>not to give place to the Devil.</hi> And in like manner has he not alſo told us by St <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 Ep. 5. 9. <hi>that we ſhould reſiſt the Devil, being ſtedfaſt in the faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſurely if we are to reſiſt him, and to give no place unto him, it muſt be poſſible for us to renounce him, by making all oppoſition againſt him, and all his temptations.</p>
            <p>And if it be poſſible for us thus to renounce the Devil, it cannot ſurely be impoſſible for us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all ſin, and particularly thoſe enormities which may be more peculiarly call'd the works of the Devil, as pride, malice, and envy, revenge, lying and cruelty, with ſuch like, which are his daily practice.</p>
            <p>Thoſe truly Chriſtian graces, of humility, charity, ſpeaking the truth from the heart, love, meekneſs and the like, which are plainly viſible in the lives of many Chriſtians, are evident proofs of this matter, it
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57468:6"/> being utterly impoſſible that they ſhould be ſo zealous as they are in the practices of theſe virtues, if they did not renounce and utterly abhor thoſe deviliſh pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices which are contrary thereunto.</p>
            <p>From hence alſo we may infer the poſſibility of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing the pomps and vanities of this wicked world, and the ſinful luſts of the fleſh.</hi> For as God has commanded us by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 12. 2. <hi>not to be conformed to this world, but to be transform'd by the renewing of our minds, proving what is that good and acceptable and perfect will of God.</hi> So St. <hi>John,</hi> 1 Ep. 5. 4. plainly ſuppoſes the poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of doing this, for, ſays he, <hi>this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then as to our <hi>ronouncing all the ſinful luſts of the fleſh;</hi> as we find St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſuppoſing the poſſibility of doing this, when he exhorts us, 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. 11. <hi>as ſtrangers and pilgrims to abſtain from fleſhly luſts which war againſt the ſoul,</hi> ſo we find St. <hi>Paul</hi> making it neceſſary in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to our attainment of everlaſting Salvation, telling us, Rom. 8. 13. <hi>that if we live after the fleſh we ſhall dye, but if we through the ſpirit do mortify the deeds of the body we ſhall live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, 'tis either poſſible for us to keep this part of our Baptiſmal Vow, or elſe Chriſt has no true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples in the world, for St. <hi>Paul</hi> has plainly told us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. 24. <hi>they that are Chriſts have crucified the fleſh, with their affections and luſts.</hi> Now it's not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but there are a great many ſincere Chriſtians in the world, and conſequently 'tis poſſible for us (if we be of that number) to mortifie our earthly mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and to crucifie our fleſhly luſts. Whatever therefore ſome people may pretend as to the impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of performing this part of our Baptiſmal Vow, 'tis certain they are under a great miſtake, ſince it is not poſſible either for ſin or Satan to prevail over us, but only ſo far as we yield unto them; they may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed allure and entice, but they cannot hurt us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we wilfully deliver over our ſtrength into the hands of theſe our enemies.</p>
            <p>Would we but arm our ſelves with the mind of Chriſt, firmly reſolving to ſerve the will and pleaſure
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57468:6"/> of the Almighty, we need not fear what ſin and all the powers of Hell can do againſt us.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, in our ſelves we are weak, but that which gives us the ſureſt grounds for our hopes of Victory over theſe our Enemies, is the powerful aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of God himſelf, for if he be for us, who can be againſt us? and we may be ſure that he will not be wanting to us, if we earneſtly ſeek after him, for he never fails to help thoſe that are engag'd againſt his Enemies, but will certainly derive that ſtrength and power into his People, which will at length make them more than Conquerors through his beloved Son.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore adviſe you (my Son) to be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might, do but uſe your beſt endeavours to mortifie the old man, and to crucifie the Fleſh with its affections and luſts, to ſubdue all thoſe outward vices of Luxury and Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, Revenge, Injuſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to abſtain from all appearance of evil, withdrawing the fuel of any vice, which you are in danger of, and conſtantly applying your ſelf unto God by prayer; and then you need not queſtion but you ſhall break Satans head, however he may be able to bruiſe your heel, tho' you may ſuffer a little by him, yet at laſt you ſhall be victorious over him.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, whereas we alſo promis'd in your name, that you ſhould believe all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, I ſhall not need to inſiſt upon proving the poſſibility of your believing them, there being nothing that I know of contained in that Creed, but what all Chriſtians of what perſwaſion ſoever do conſent unto.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore now paſs to the third and laſt part of your Baptiſmal Vow, <hi>which is to keep Gods holy Will and Commandments, and to walk in the ſame all the days of your Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that there is no more impoſſibility in the performance of this, than the other parts of this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn vow, we have the plain Teſtimony of our bleſſed Saviour, who for our greater encouragement has told us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 28, 29. <hi>that his commands are ſo</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57468:7"/> 
               <hi>far from being intolerable, that they are eaſy and full of Comfort, for,</hi> ſays he, <hi>take my yoke upon you and learn of me, and ye ſhall find reſt unto your Souls, for my yoke is eaſy and my burthen is light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And St. <hi>John</hi> the beloved diſciple in like manner aſſures us that as our keeping the Commandments of God is the beſt evidence of our love to him, ſo they are all reaſonable and every way ſuitable to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of mankind, as 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 5. 3. <hi>this is the love of God that we keep his Commandments, and his Commandments are not grievous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now altho theſe Texts of Scripture might be ſufficient, one would think, to put the matter beyond all diſpute, yet becauſe it is poſſible you may meet with ſome unreaſonable men, who will be ready to ask you as they have done me, whether there was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any man in the World that was able to do theſe things; I ſhall now give ſome few examples of good and pious men, who (as we may conclude from what is ſaid of them) found it poſſible through the grace of God to renounce the Devil, the World and the Fleſh, and to walk before God in purity and holineſs of Life, yielding ſuch an uniform obedience to all his Commands as he was pleaſed to accept of.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place therefore, may we not reaſonably ſuppoſe that <hi>Noah</hi> did this, it being ſaid of him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>that he was a juſt man, and perfect in his generation, and that he walked with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what reaſon have we to doubt of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s doing the ſame thing, who as he was the father of the faithful, ſo he manifeſted the ſincerity of his faith by the uniformity of his obedience; for as St. <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>ch.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>Faith wrought with his works, and by works was faith made perfect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like manner, may we not conclude the ſame thing of <hi>Job,</hi> of whom the Lord himſelf was pleaſed to give this character, <hi>ch.</hi> 1. 8. <hi>that there was none like him in all the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feared God, and eſchewed evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And tho Satan moved God againſt him, as it is ſaid <hi>ch.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>to deſtroy him without a cauſe,</hi> yet the Lord
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57468:7"/> would not do it, for he ſaw that notwithſtanding all thoſe afflictions which were befallen him, he ſtill held faſt his Integrity.</p>
            <p>And what ſhall we ſay of <hi>David,</hi> unto whom as we read, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 22. the Lord himſelf gave teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, <hi>and ſaid I have found</hi> David <hi>the Son of</hi> Jeſſe, <hi>a man after my own heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, he grievouſly offended God more than once, but then it is to be conſidered, that the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his repentance made amends for all. And we have no reaſon to doubt, but that God was pleaſed to accept of his hearty ſorrow, inſtead of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe and many other holy men under the Law, were able through the Divine aſſiſtance, ſo to walk before God as to be approved of him, how little reaſon have we to doubt of the poſſibility of the ſame things being done by Chriſtians, now under the more glorious light and gracious diſpenſation of the Goſpel? Why may not we now (as St <hi>Paul</hi> tells us he did) <hi>exerciſe our ſelves in keeping a good Conſcience void of offence towards God and towards man?</hi> It muſt be confeſs'd, that we are far from being able of our ſelves to do theſe things, but as St <hi>Paul</hi> declared of himſelf, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 13. <hi>So we may aſſure our ſelves that we may be able to do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengthens us;</hi> and we need not in the leaſt doubt of his aſſiſtance, upon our humble requeſt at the Throne of Grace for the ſame.</p>
            <p>So that now (my Son) you ſee how reaſonably thoſe people argue againſt our Baptiſmal Vow, which contains nothing in it but what God has commanded, and good men have practic'd. Let no man therefore deceive you, and ſay that we have promis'd more in your name than it's poſſible for you to perform, for if you will but in good earneſt oppoſe theſe enemies of your Soul, the World, the Fleſh and the Devil, you'll find the bleſſing of God concurring with your holy reſolutions; he that hath planted theſe things in your heart, will alſo water, and make them abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly fruitful, to the confuſion of Satan, the glory of God, and the eternal Salvation of your immortal Soul.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57468:8"/>
            <p> And now having prov'd unto you, the poſſibility of keeping your Baptiſmal Vow, I ſhall in the</p>
            <p>3d place ſhew you how great an obligation you lye under to obſerve it.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe I might produce many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſundry Texts of Scripture, but becauſe I rather deſire to inform your judgment than burthen your memory, I ſhall comprehend what I have to ſay upon this head in as few words as I can. You muſt therefore know, and be convinc'd of this, that your eternal happineſs depends upon your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious obſervation of this vow. 'Tis impoſſible for you to be made partakers of the mercies of God in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, without repentance, faith, and new obedience.</p>
            <p>For, as our Saviour has told us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 17. that <hi>if we will enter into life we muſt keep the Commandments;</hi> ſo St <hi>Paul</hi> has told us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6. <hi>that without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God,</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle has alſo declar'd, Rom. 8. 13. <hi>That if we live after the fleſh we ſhall dye, but if through the ſpirit we do mortifie the deeds of the body, we ſhall live.</hi> For theſe are the terms of the Covenant of grace between God and us, that he will be graciouſly pleas'd to beſtow upon us the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſins, and everlaſting life; but it is upon this condition, that we perform our part of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to believe, and to do thoſe things that we have promi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d in our Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>And this is ſo plain, that I do not think there is any need of inſiſting upon the proof of it, becauſe in all Covenants the party promiſing any benefits or priviledges, is no farther oblig'd to make them good, than the other party performs the duties promis'd and required on his part.</p>
            <p>So that as you love your own Soul, and deſire to be for ever happy in the life to come, it highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you to be very mindful of your Baptiſmal Vow, and careful to obſerve it.</p>
            <p>But withal I would entreat you ſeriouſly to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this one thing, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the World, and ſuffered the curſed death of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57468:8"/> Croſs, on purpoſe to purifie us; and therefore ſhall we ſtill continue in our filthineſs and impurities? he gave himſelf for us, at it's ſaid, Titus 2. 14. <hi>that he might red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em us from all iniquity, and purify unto himſelf a peculiar people zealous of good works;</hi> and how then can we ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the face to delight in ſin? why then ſhould we thus prejudiee our own Souls? why ſhould we deſtroy our ſelves, after all the care and pains that our Bleſſed Lord has been at to ſave us?</p>
            <p>Have we more love for Satan than we have for God, that we ſhould make a ſcruple of renouncing the Devil both in our words and works? have we more affection for ſin that will ruin us, than for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, that will be a means to ſave us? through Chriſt we are made the Children of God by Adoption, and heirs through Grace of his Everlaſting Kingdom, and ſhall we be ſuch fools as to ſell our Birth-right, like <hi>Eſau,</hi> for one ſinful morſel, and to deſtroy both Souls and Bodies for evermore.</p>
            <p>Let me entreat you (my Son) to lay theſe things ſeriouſly to heart, and be perſwaded ſo to lead your life here, that you may be for ever happy in the life to come; for as you may learn from the words of the Apoſtle, 1 Cor. 15. laſt, <hi>if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſtedfaſt and immoveable, always abounding in the work of the Lord, you may be aſſured that your labour ſhall n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be in vain in the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that altho it be certain th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is no other Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice now under the Goſpel, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that of Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs, which can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icient to ſatisfy Gods juſtice, expiate our ſin and obtain Eternal Redemption for us, yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches us, Rom. 12. 1. <hi>that the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng our B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iving Sacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fice holy acceptable unto God is our r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſonable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vice:</hi> So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho the ſacrifice of our ſelves wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch we ought to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up to God in keeping our Baptiſmal Vow cannot procure Salvation, yet it is abſolutely neceſſary for our reception of it. And therefore inſtead of liſtning to thoſe perſons who are wont to argue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the poſſibility of their duty, and like the faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57468:9"/> 
               <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> (when they return'd from taking a view of the promiſed Land) cry out, who ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand before theſe mighty Gyants? how is it poſſible for any man to keep this Vow? inſtead of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an ear to ſuch people, I ſay, if you will give up your ſelf in earneſt to the practice of holineſs, and heartily pray to the Lord for the gracious aſſiſtance of his holy Spirit, tho you may probably find ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in your firſt onſet, yet it's certain that when once you are got into the way of it, you'll find the practice of holineſs one of the eaſieſt and pleaſanteſt things in the whole world, you'll take no greater pleaſure in any thing than in denying your ſelf, nor find any greater comfort in the world, than in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the victory over it.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall conclude this head with thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent words of our Church, at the latter end of the office for Baptiſm, where we are told that <hi>Baptiſm doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>preſent unto us our profeſſion, which is to follow the example of our Saviour Chriſt, and to be made like unto him, that as he died and roſe again for us, ſo ſhould we who are baptiz'd dye for ſin, and riſe again unto righteouſneſs, continually mortifying all our evil and corrupt affections, and daily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in all virtue, and godlineſs of living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I hope you will ſee no reaſon for neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting to be confirm'd, but (as our Church has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd the meaning of this word) that <hi>being now come to the years of diſcretion and underſtanding, what your God-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and God-mothers promiſed for you in Baptiſm, you your ſelf with your own mouth and conſent openly, before the Church, will ratify and confirm the ſame, and alſo promiſe that by the Grace of God, you will evermore endeavour your ſelf, faithfully to obſerve ſuch things as you by your own confeſſion have aſſented unto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here's nothing impoſſible (as I have ſhew'd) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of you, nothing that's truly difficult to a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mind, aſſiſted by the Grace of Gods holy Spirit, which is never wanting to thoſe that heartily ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it: nothing finally but what is attended with the greateſt comfort and ſatisfaction of mind in this life, and which will render us capable through Jeſus Chriſt of eternal glory in the life to come.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57468:9"/>
            <p> Whenſoever therefore you ſhall be inform'd of the Biſhops intention to confirm the youth of this Dioceſs, I deſire you not to neglect the firſt opportunity, but take the beſt care you can to prepare your ſelf for it, by faſting and prayer ſome time before, ſeriouſly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating upon that ſolemn vow, which you are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new in the preſence of Almighty God.</p>
            <p>And when the time comes (if no unavoidable acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhall hinder you) repair to the place appointed with all poſſible ſeriouſneſs, and compoſedneſs of mind, there ſtanding before the Biſhop give diligent attention to him, while he asks you, together with the reſt, <hi>whether you do in the preſence of God, and that Congregation, renew the ſolemn promiſe and vow that was made in your name at your Baptiſm, ratifying and confirming the ſame in your own perſon, and acknowledging your ſelf to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and to do all thoſe things which your Godfathers and Godmothers then undertook for you;</hi> and then make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer with an audible, but yet humble voice, and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſtian courage, ſaying <hi>I do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, be ſure that you heartily join with the Bp in his prayers to God for you, and all that are then confirm'd, and when he ſhall lay his hand upon your head, praying over you while you kneel before him, let your devout affections go along with your words, ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> heartily to that, as to all the other Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, when the Bp has pronounc'd the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſee that you depart with a joyful and glad heart, and yet humbly praiſing God in your mind, that he has ſpar'd your life till that time, and given you an opportunity of engaging your ſelf perſonally in his Service, from which you muſt reſolve to let no temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the world, the Devil, or the fleſh, ever draw you, but that you will continue Chriſts faithful Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier and Servant to your lives end.</p>
            <p>And now, my Son, having thus explain'd your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal vow, ſhew'd you the poſſibility of keeping it, and the abſolute neceſſity there is for you ſo to do, in order to your Everlaſting Salvation; I have ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things to recommend to your pious conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57468:10"/> and which (as I have opportunity) I ſhall either do by word or writing, but at preſent, I ſhall only give you my advice in reference to your conſtant attendance upon the publick worſhip of God, and the manner of your behaviour therein.</p>
            <p>For having obſerv'd (not without great trouble of ſpirit) that as ſome are ſo luke-warm in Religion, that they do not care how ſeldom they go to Church, ſo they do not matter how irreverently they behave themſelves in the Houſe of God, and conſequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive little or no benefit by their being there; I have thought it convenient to give you ſome few inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in theſe matters alſo, which if you will be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to obſerve and practiſe, you may then through the Grace of God be edify'd by frequenting the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Aſſemblies of his People, and by leading the reſt of your life accordingly, may at laſt obtain the eternal Salvation of your precious Soul.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Therefore as to your giving conſtant attendance upon the publick worſhip of God, I cannot but think it highly neceſſary in this looſe and degenerate age, to give you my advice in this matter, it being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly obſerv'd, that many young people following the ill example of thoſe, who are old enough to have more knowledge than they ſeem to have by their way of living, are very negligent herein, either loytering at home, rambling about the Fields, or gadding from houſe to houſe, when they ſhould be waiting upon God in the Houſe of Prayer.</p>
            <p>You muſt know therefore, that whereas God has allow'd us ſix days in the week to labour in, and to do all that we have to do, in reference to our world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns, commanding us to reſt the ſeventh day, he never intended hereby, that we ſhould give up our ſelves to idleneſs and vanity on that day, or to ſpend it in drowſineſs and ſleep, much leſs in ſports and drunkenneſs, but the will and command of the Lord is, that we ſhould remember to keep it Holy, <hi>i. e.</hi> to ſpend that day in religious exerciſe, giving up our ſelves to the ſervice of God, both publickly and privately, but each in its proper ſeaſon.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57468:10"/>
            <p> Thus we find that as the ſeventh day from the beginning was religiouſly obſerved, in memory of the Creator of all things, ſo the firſt day of the week, ever ſince the Apoſtles times, hath been piouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Chriſtian Church in memory of our Saviours reſurrection, as being the conſummation of the great work of our Redemption.</p>
            <p>Let me therefore adviſe you be very careful in ſpending the Lords Day, in ſuch a manner as that God may be thereby moſt glorified, and this certainly you cannot do better than employing your ſelf in the publick prayers, and other religious exerciſes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the congregation.</p>
            <p>For however private devotions, when duly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in their proper ſeaſon, may be accepted of God, yet we do edify one another, as well as Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy God, moſt by the mutual examples and union of our publick devotions.</p>
            <p>So that the Lord having been ſo liberal as to allow us ſix days for our ſelves, reſerving but one in the week for his more ſolemn worſhip and ſervice, how can any of us have the face to rob him of that day by ſpending it any otherwiſe, than to his honour and glory.</p>
            <p>Satan, I doubt not, will be ready to tempt you ſometimes in this caſe, as he tempted our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in reference to the forbidden Fruit, and as he then upbraided God with niggardlineſs, in that he had not given them freedom to eat of all the Trees in the Garden, inſinuating as if the Lord had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrainted them from the uſe of that one, out of ſome ſelf-end; for, ſaid the Serpent, the Lord doth know, that in the day you eat thereof, you ſhall be as God, knowing good and evil. I doubt not, I ſay, but as Satan dealt with our firſt parents in reference to the forbidden fruit, ſo may he deal with you, in reference to the Lords Day, inſinuating as if it were very hard, that you may not take your liberty, and recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate your ſelf on that day, being tir'd with the toyl and labour of all the week beſide.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57468:11"/>
            <p> But, my Son, have a care of Satans ſubtilty, and let the conſideration of Gods bounty to us in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, anſwer all the ſly ſuggeſtions of the wicked one.</p>
            <p>For if God had been pleaſed to allow us but one day for our uſe, and reſerve ſix wholly for his own, we ſhould have had no reaſon to have complained, he being our Creator, and we the work of his hands, but ſince he has been ſo liberal as to grant us ſix days for our Worldly buſineſs, and reſerved one only wholly to himſelf, we are the moſt unreaſonable creatures in the World, if we are not content with ſo liberal a proportion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſtrive to the utmoſt of our power to glorify him on that day, according to his own appointment.</p>
            <p>Whenſoever therefore you are tempted to abſent your ſelves from the publick Worſhip of God, give no entertainment to any ſuch temptation, but reject it with an indignation. like that of <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton miſtreſs, and ſay, how can I do this great wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and ſin againſt God.</p>
            <p>Have a care of being ſo unjuſt and ungrateful to God, upon whom you have your whole dependance, as to be ſeduced by the ill example of thoſe profane people in this licentious age, who are ſo inſenſible of the grace and mercy of God in Chriſt Jeſus, that altho without that they are liable to periſh every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but through the Divine patience and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance are ſuffered to live year after year, yet cannot find in their hearts to ſpend that one day in the Lords ſervice, which he has purpoſely ſet apart for his own more ſolemn worſhip. Our bleſſed Saviour, as St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells in the parable of the wiſe Steward, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 43. <hi>has pronounced the Servant bleſſed, whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find faithful,</hi> and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſcharging his duty; but what ſhall become then of thoſe profane People, whom the Lord if he ſhould come to judgement, according to the ancient tradition of the Church upon the Lords day, ſhall find either ſleeping upon their Beds, or buſying themſelves about the World, making proviſion for the Fleſh
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57468:11"/> to fulfil the luſts thereof, or any way gratifying their ſenſual appetites, inſtead of doing the work of the Lord. Do you think that if that terrible day of the Lord ſhall come at ſuch a time, it will not be infinitely more comfortable to be found upon your Knees, lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up your Heart in prayer to God, and praiſing him with a chearful voice, in giving attention to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of his holy Word, or finally in exerciſing your ſelf ſome way or other to the glory of God.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you my advice in reference to your conſtant attendance upon the publick worſhip of God, I ſhall in the 2d place, ſhew you in what manner you ought to behave your ſelf in the Congregation of Gods people, that ſo your going thither may be for the better and not for the worſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore you muſt conſider this, that when you go to ſerve the Lord in thoſe places, which are ſet apart for Divine Worſhip, you then go into Gods more eſpecial preſence. For ſo <hi>David</hi> teſtifies, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 100. 1, 2. <hi>Where he exhorts the Jews to praiſe God the more chearfully in the Temple, as being the ſpecial place of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious preſence. O come,</hi> ſays he, <hi>let us ſing unto the Lord, let us heartily rejoice in the ſtrength of our Salvation. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t us come before his preſence with thankſgiving, and ſhew our ſelves glad in him with Pſalms.</hi> And becauſe we ſhould not think that he is leſs preſent now in the religious Aſſemblies of Chriſtians than he was in the Jewiſh Temple, our Saviour has expreſly declared, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 20. <hi>that when two or three are gathered together in his name, he is there in the midſt of them.</hi> And you may be ſure, that if he will vouchſafe to honour ſo ſmall a number with his preſence, as two or three ſo aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to do him worſhip and ſervice, he will not deny his gracious preſence to the greateſt Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
            <p>And upon the account of ſuch places being dedicated to the ſervice of God, and of his being more eſpecially preſent in them, upon theſe accounts I ſuppoſe it was that St <hi>Paul</hi> reproved the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſo ſeverely for their rude behaviour in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 22. <hi>what,</hi> ſays he, <hi>have you not houſes to eat and to drink in, or deſpiſe ye the Church of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:57468:12"/>
            <p> Your heart therefore being thus prepoſeſſeſt with an awful dread and reverence of the Divine preſence in the houſe of prayer, I would adviſe you in the 2d place to make a ſutable preparation before you enter into the houſe of God.</p>
            <p>See that you order your neceſſary buſineſs therefore every Lords Day in the morning, ſo as that you may go to Church before the beginning of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>But before you go, among other preparations, I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to read over the Pſalms, the firſt and ſecond Leſſons, as alſo the Epiſtle and Goſpel appointed for that day, and as you read, obſerve and meditate upon the moſt material paſſages contained therein, and if there be any thing more remarkable than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, which you do not underſtand, be not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to deſire information of any in the Family that may be able to give it.</p>
            <p>By this means you will be better able to read thoſe portions of Scripture with the Miniſter in time of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice more attentively, and in all probability the Holy Spirit may then dart more pious thoughts into your mind, and more enlighten your underſtanding than it did upon your firſt reading them over in private.</p>
            <p>Having thus exerciſed your ſelf till it is time for you to go to Church, ſo ſoon as you are got thither, ſee that you do not loyter in the Church yard, neither make it your buſineſs to diſcourſe with others about any worldly matters (unleſs it be a word or two of very great neceſſity) for you will be in great danger of having thoſe things run in your mind, and diſtract your thoughts in time of divine ſervice, which you have much diſcourſed of juſt before.</p>
            <p>Repair therefore to your Seat or uſual place in the Church, and falling upon your Knees offer up to God this or the like prayer, with the moſt devout affection, <hi>Holineſs O Lord becomes thine Houſe for ever, and therefore I beſeech thee ſo to aſſiſt me with thy holy Spirit, that I may offer unto thy divine Majeſty ſuch a lively ſacrifice of prayer and praiſes as may be accepted through thy beloved Son; and grant alſo, that I may ſo hear thy holy word, and attend to the</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57468:12"/> 
               <hi>Doctrine of the preacher, that I may daily grow in grace and godlineſs and ſpiritual ſtrength, thro our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, Amen.</hi> When you have thus privately begg'd the Divine aſſiſtance, you may then do well to exerciſe your ſelf in pious meditations, or in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome portion of Gods word, till the publick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Church begins, which that you may be the better able to join in with all your Heart and Soul, together with all thoſe devour Chriſtians, who make conſcience of waiting upon God in his holy Temple, I adviſe you in the</p>
            <p>3d place, to be throughly acquainted with every part of the Common Prayer, which you may do it to your ſatisfaction, by a frequent and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous peruſal, together with an impartial conſideration thereof, for I am fully perſwaded, that none are ſo ready to deſpiſe it as thoſe who are leaſt acquainted with it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not therefore now give you a particular account of its method, or of that admirable connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is obſervable between the ſeveral parts of it, (for theſe things are already done by ſome pious and learned Divines of our Church,) but ſhall only ſhow you the neceſſity of that reverence, which is due to the Majeſty of that great and glorious God, whom we are to worſhip when we aſſemble our ſelves together in thoſe places which are dedicated to his ſervice.</p>
            <p>You muſt know therefore that the Reverence which we owe to Almighty God is twofold.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Inward, which is that of our Souls.</item>
               <item>2. Outward, which is that of our Bodies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt place, when you come to worſhip the Lord, you muſt be ſure to ſanctifie him in your Heart, yielding unto him that inward and ſpiritual worſhip which is due to his infinite Majeſty, and this you muſt do by believing in him, fearing him, and loving him, with all your heart, and with all your mind, with all your ſoul, and with all your ſtrength. For when our hearts are deeply affected with the love of God, our ſervice will be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the more chearful.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57468:13"/>
            <p> But yet we muſt not ſo love him as to neglect the getting our hearts alſo poſſeſt with an awful dread and reverence of his glorious Majeſty, for <hi>David</hi> tells us in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 89. 7. <hi>that God is greatly to be feared in the Congregation of Saints, and to be had in reverence of all thoſe that are about him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When our hearts therefore are thus poſſeſt both with a reverential fear and love of God, we ſhall then alſo be more careful to cleanſe them from all impure and worldly thoughts, and fix them with due attention upon thoſe acts of Religion, wherein we are exercis'd.</p>
            <p>Thus, as the more inward parts of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Temple were ſtill more and more beautiful and glorious, ſo we who profeſs Chriſtianity, and are ſaid to be the Temple of the living God, ſhould be very careful that all the thoughts and intentions of our hearts be holy and ſpiritual, every way ſo prepared and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd, that the Lord may be pleas'd to take up his reſidence in our hearts, when we draw nigh to ſerve him. But then</p>
            <p n="2">2. You muſt have a care, that under a pretence of inward ſanctity, you do not deſtroy all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward decency; for as in the firſt Commandment the Lord requires the inward and ſpiritual worſhip of your heart, and therein doth more eſpecially de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, ſo in the ſecond Commandment we are forbid to give any religious outward worſhip to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Now by this we are to underſtand, that the Lord expects that homage from us; and challenges it as peculiarly due to himſelf becauſe his honour and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority are hereby upheld greatly in the world.</p>
            <p>So that we muſt not think it enough at all times to glorify God in our Spirits only, but upon ſome occaſions, and eſpecially when God is publickly worſhipped by us, we ought to glorify him in our Bodies alſo.</p>
            <p>And the reaſon hereof, as St <hi>Paul</hi> has plainly told us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 20. is becauſe he has not only created but redeemed both Soul and Body. <hi>Ye are bought with</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57468:13"/> 
               <hi>a price,</hi> ſays he, <hi>therefore glorify God in your Body and in your Spirit, which are Gods.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that you ſee both Soul and Body ſhould joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in all thoſe acts of devotion whereby God is glorified.</p>
            <p>For as to pretend that we can worſhip God ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently with our Souls only, ſhows too much irreverence and rudeneſs in his preſence, ſo to imagine that we have no more to do, than to be exact in all our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward geſtures, is the greateſt Hypocriſy.</p>
            <p>We have no reaſon, it's true, to doubt, but in ſome caſes the Lord may accept the inward devotion of our hearts, when we are not in a Capacity, or have not an opportunity of giving any outward teſtimonies of it; but we have no reaſon at all to hope for his acceptance of a few bare bodily actions, while our hearts are wholly unconcern'd in his ſervice.</p>
            <p>Thus having ſhewed you the neceſſity both of that inward and outward reverence, which we owe to God in his publick worſhip, I ſhall in the next place take notice of thoſe particular expreſſions of reverence to which we are obliged by the word of God, the rules of our Church agreeable thereunto, and to all which the practice of good and pious men in all ages have been conformable.</p>
            <p>Now this outward reverence you muſt know may either be expreſſed by words or actions.</p>
            <p>In words we reverence God (provided always that our Hearts go along with our Tongues) when we confeſs our ſins unto him, and offer up our prayers and praiſes with an audible Voice.</p>
            <p>And this is undoubtedly a very great priviledge, that the whole Congregation in ſome parts of Divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice are admitted to joyn with the Miniſter in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up their devotions unto God, and we ſhould rejoyce in this Liberty, eſpecially ſince by this means we teſtifie to one another, how ready we are with one Heart and one Mouth to glorify God.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo to be conſider'd, that the people bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a part with the Miniſter in the publick devotion may very much tend to the more inflaming one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57468:14"/> devout affections, and to the better fixing our mind in a diligent attendance upon our duty, and ſo to the rendring our devotions the more accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <p>Under the Law, the people indeed were to bring their ſacrifices and oblations to the Temple, but the Prieſts only were to offer them up.</p>
            <p>Whereas now under the gracious diſpenſation of the Goſpel, the people are ſo far become Prieſts unto God, as to be admitted the honour of bearing a part together with the Prieſt in his publick worſhip.</p>
            <p>And to this great priviledge the works of St. <hi>Peter</hi> (as I ſuppoſe) may have relation, 1 Ep. 2. 5. <hi>Where ſpeaking of the whole Congregation of Chriſtians,</hi> he tells us, <hi>that we are built up a ſpiritual houſe, an holy Prieſthood, to offer up Spiritual ſacrifices, acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore you ſhould be ſure to accompany the Miniſter with a pure heart and humble voice unto the Throne of the Heavenly Grace, as in repeating the Confeſſion and the Lord's Prayer after him, ſo in making all ſuch anſwers as you are directed by the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick throughout the whole ſervice, never omitting to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> but thus in a fervent zeal ſhutting up all your Prayers.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I find that the generality of Chriſtians are negligent in this, to the end that you may not follow the ill examples of others, and be ſo too, I ſhall now take occaſion to inform you rightly in this matter, by ſhewing you,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of all, the meaning of the word <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. That the people of God in all ages of the Church have made uſe of this word in their publick devotion.</item>
               <item>3. How great a neceſſity there is that this practice ſhould beſtill continued among us.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt place, as to this word <hi>Amen.</hi> It is the ſame in all Languages, and the people of all Nations upon Earth, make uſe of it at the concluſion of their Prayers.</p>
            <p>And as to the meaning of it, it's cheifly twofold; oft it ſignifies either <hi>ſo be it</hi> or <hi>ſo it is.</hi> Sometime we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Amen,</hi> and thereby expreſs our hearty deſire that the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57468:14"/> thing which we have prayed for may be granted, and in this ſenſe we uſe it at the end of all our prayers; ſometime alſo we uſe this word to teſtifie our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and the declaration of our faith, aſſuring our ſelves thereby that the things which we profeſs to believe are certainly true, and in this ſenſe we uſe it after the Doxology, or <hi>Glory be to the Father, &amp;c.</hi> and the Creed. And in both theſe ſenſes we find it us'd in Scripture, as I ſhall ſhew you, by obſerving in the</p>
            <p>2d place, that the people of God in all ages of the Church have made uſe of it in their publick devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, as to the Church of God under the legal diſpenſation, we read <hi>Nehemiah</hi> 8. 6. that <hi>when Ezra bleſſed the Lord the great God, all the people anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Amen, lifting up their hands;</hi> and no doubt but their hearts were alſo lifted up with the greateſt fervency, as appeared by their doubling the expreſſion, ſaying <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, we find <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. 14. that even when the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites did uſe to perform divine ſervice, and declare the curſe of God to be due to ſuch and ſuch ſinners, the whole Congregation were to anſwer <hi>and ſay A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, i. e.</hi> be it ſo, or curſed be the man who does thoſe things. Thus they were to declare their abhorrence of thoſe things which were ſo eminently liable to the curſe of God.</p>
            <p>And here by the way I cannot but obſerve, that if all of us were duly ſenſible of the great indignation of God againſt thoſe ſins, againſt which the curſe of God is denounc'd in his holy word, we ſhould have a care of falling into, or however of perſevering im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitently in any of thoſe ſins mention'd in the Commination, which is appointed to be read on <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday,</hi> and then we ſhould not ſcruple to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> at the end of every ſentence, as many do, fearing thereby to call for a curſe upon themſelves. For tho in ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> we affirm with our own mouths the curſe of God to be due to ſuch ſins, which is no more than what <hi>David</hi> has declared <hi>P.</hi> 119.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57468:15"/> 21. ſaying <hi>curſed are all they, that do err from thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> yet 'tis certain we ſhall not be found liable to the curſe, if we be not guilty of the ſin; and if we be guilty, and perſevere therein impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tently, whether we ſay <hi>Amen</hi> or no, we ſhall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be accurſed at the laſt day, for as we read <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 41. <hi>then ſhall the Righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth ſay unto them on the left hand, depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to the practice of the Jewiſh Church in ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> we find that they did not only uſe this word at the end of their Prayers, but in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion alſo of their Pſalms and Hymns, as we read 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 16. 36. for at the end of that Pſalm, which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id</hi> had compos'd for the uſe of the Temple, all the people were required to ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was it uſed by the Jews only under the Law, but from the beginning of the Goſpel diſpenſation it has been practis'd alſo by he Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>That it was us'd in the Apoſtles times is evident 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 16. For there St <hi>Paul</hi> reproving thoſe who prayed at any time in a Language which the people did not underſtand, he uſes this as an argument to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove the unreaſonableneſs of that practice, becauſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e People, who underſtood not the Language, could not ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to ſuch prayers, they could tnot give their conſent to what they did not underſtand.</p>
            <p>Nor did the Apoſtles only think ſit to conclude all prayers with this word, but our Saviour was pleaſed alſo to teach us ſo to do, for <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>we find the Lords Prayer concluding with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as this was the practice of Gods people both under the Law, and in the beginning of the Goſpel diſpenſation, ſo it has been continued in the Church of Chriſt ever ſince, tho of late years through the great want of Zeal and true Devotion, it has been much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by us in this nation.</p>
            <p>But how great a neceſſity there is, that this anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent practice of all the peoples ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers of the Church, ought to be continued among us, I ſhall now proceed in the</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57468:15"/>
            <p> 3d place to ſhow you. For whereas there are two things among ſeveral others neceſſarily required in prayer to make it acceptable unto God, <hi>viz.</hi> a fervent deſire and lively Faith, we give a teſtimony of both theſe in ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> but in neglecting this, we ſeem to be as by-ſtanders, and no way concerned in the things that are prayed for, nor in the ſervice which is performed.</p>
            <p>And in truth how good ſoever the prayers be, you have no reaſon to expect the benefit of them, unleſs you heartily joyn in them.</p>
            <p>If another man writes a Letter in your name, you ought to ſet your hand to it, ot make your mark to teſtify your conſent unto that which is written; and thus if the Miniſter prays for you, you ought to ſet your Hand and Seal to his prayer (ſuppoſing the matter of it to be good) by ſaying <hi>Amen</hi> to it, nor ſhould you think it enough to ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to all the prayers of the Church, but you ſhould alſo take delight in bearing a part with your brethren in making the Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſinging Pſalms, and in all other parts of Divine ſervice.</p>
            <p>And this you will certainly do, when once you have got your heart ſincerely affected with a ſenſe of Gods infinite love and mercy toward you. For ſo we find King <hi>David</hi> ſpeaking of himſelf, and telling us that the great experience which he had of Gods love to him, influenced him ſo much, that he could not refrain from ſinging praiſes to him. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 63. <hi>becauſe thy loving kindneſs is better than life, my lips ſhall praiſe thee,</hi> again <hi>v.</hi> 5. <hi>my Soul ſhall be ſatisfied as with marrow and fatneſs when my mouth praiſeth thee with joyful lips.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor did that pious King deſire to be ſingular in this matter, for in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 95. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>he encourages all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the like practice, ſaying, O come let us ſing unto the Lord, let us heartily rejoyce in the ſtrength of our Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, as you are to reverence God by opening your lips, that your mouth may ſhew forth his praiſe, ſo you are to reverence him by your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and geſtures, as by lifting up your hands and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57468:16"/> eyes in prayer to God, ſtanding up at the recital of the Creed, Hymns and Goſpel; by kneeling, or at leaſt ſtanding up in time of Prayer, and keeping your head uncovered all the time of divine ſervice; and while the Miniſter is preaching, I ſay that you are to kneel, or at leaſt to ſtand up in time of prayer, becauſe both are allowed to be agreeable to the word of God and the practice of good men: but I muſt needs ſay that kneeling is much more commendable, and a better way of expreſſing your humility, than ſtanding up is when you pray to God.</p>
            <p>In ſome caſes, it's true ſtanding up in time of prayer is not to be blamed, as in the caſe of ſome natural infirmity, when a man cannot kneel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out very great pain and uneaſineſs, or when a Congregation is ſo much crowded, that it would be very inconvenient or impoſſible to do it, or when the rules of the Church require it, as it does of the Miniſter for very good reaſons in ſome parts of divine ſervice, even when the people are required to kneel. In theſe I ſay (and perhaps there may be ſome other the like) caſes, to pray ſtanding is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveable.</p>
            <p>But then in ſuch caſes, you ſhould take care to give ſome other demonſtrations of your humility, faith and reverence, as by lifting up your hands and eyes to Heaven, by ſmitting your breaſt, and the like.</p>
            <p>For to ſtand up all the time of prayer, when you are required to kneel down, and may do it without any inconvenience to your ſelf to others. and never ſo much as open your lips, or move your hands and eyes in honour to God, is a ſhrewd ſign, that there's but very little true devotion in your heart.</p>
            <p>But for ſitting ſtill all the time of Prayer, as too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do; this (my Son) I muſt needs tell you is not only the greateſt irreverence, but a moſt rude and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly behaviour in the more eſpecial preſence of God and his holy Angels.</p>
            <p>And how much ſoever thoſe people who won't be diſſwaded from it, may pretend to honour God in their hearts, yet 'tis certain they diſhonour him before
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57468:16"/> men, which I am ſure is a very great provocation, for the Lord hath ſaid, them that honour me I will honour, but they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteemed. I will not pretend to judge the ſecrets of ſuch mens hearts, but let them ask their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences what the reaſon is that they kneel down to prayer in their own houſes, and yet fit down all the time of Prayer in the Houſe of God, and then tell me whether the true reaſon of their irreverence in the Church dos not proceed from their want of a true love and reſpect for the publick ſervice, and if ſo, where's their ſincerity.</p>
            <p>For as it may reaſonably be ſuſpected, that that pretended inviſible piety, which is not attended with viſible purity, is a falſe, or rather no piety at all, and that thoſe perſons who make no conſcience of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God publickly, take little or no care to ſerve him privately, ſo it may without breach of charity be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that thoſe perſons, who refuſe to give unto God the outward reverence of their Bodies in the publick congregation, where he is more eſpecially to be honoured, have but very little reverence toward him in the heart.</p>
            <p>For if they kneel down to prayer in their own Houſes, out of a hearty reverence to God they are certainly much more obliged to do it in the houſe of prayer, becauſe in ſo doing they give a more publick Teſtimony of that honour and reverence which is due to the Almighty.</p>
            <p>It is very obſervable, that in the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi>'s days, as we read <hi>Ch.</hi> 1. 7. the People were come to that degree of Profaneneſs, that they thought any thing was good enough to be offered up in ſacrifice to the Lord, and yet ſtill they would be thought to have a mighty reverence for him and his worſhip: but ſee how God reſented their irreverent behaviour toward him, a Son, ſays he, honoureth his Father, and a Servant his Maſter, If I then be a Father, where is my honour, and if I be a Maſter where is my fear. And yet notwithſtanding the contempt of the Lord and his Ordinances, they would be ſtill ready to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57468:17"/> themſelves, and ſay <hi>wherein have we deſpiſed thy name, and wherein have we polluted thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore the Lord tells them plainly, that they had diſhonoured him, in thinking that it was no great matter, what it was that they offer'd in Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, any thing as they thought was good enough to be killed.</p>
            <p>So that the Lord would have them conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an earthly Prince would be pleaſed with a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that ſhould behave himſelf toward him in ſuch a manner, <hi>if ye offer the blind for Sacrifice is it not evil, and if ye offer the lame and the ſick is it not evil, offer it now unto thy Governor, will he be pleaſed with thee, or accept thy perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you ſee, that however ſome people may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to an inward reverence of God, while they give no outward Teſtimony of it in their words and actions, yet the Lord is not ſatisfied with it, he does not think himſelf to be honoured by thoſe ways which our ſuperiours take to be a diſhonour to them.</p>
            <p>For ſhould theſe perſons behave themſelves in the preſence of an earthly King, or of an inferiour Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, as they do in the preſence of the King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, they would be lookt upon to be very rude and unmannerly; and it cannot reaſonably be ſuppoſed, but that the Almighty God will in like manner reſent the behaviour of thoſe, who act direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to that rule preſcribed in his holy words, <hi>of doing all things in his worſhip decently and in order;</hi> moſt certain it is that all the holy men of old, I mean the religious Kings and Prieſts and Prophets before Chriſt were of this opinion: and therefore we read often of their kneeling down, and ſometime of their ſtanding up, but never of their ſitting down, when they went to Prayer.</p>
            <p>Thus we read, 2 Chr. 6. 13. <hi>Of King</hi> Solomon's <hi>kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down upon his knees.</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n. 6. 10. <hi>of</hi> Daniel<hi>'s kneeling down</hi> 3 <hi>times a day and praying.</hi> Ez. 9. 5. <hi>of</hi> Ezrah<hi>'s falling upon his knees and ſpreading out his hands to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57468:17"/>
            <p> Nor was this outward reverence peculiar to the Church of God before Chriſt, for under the New Teſtament we find it alſo practis'd as well by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelf as his Diſciples. For Luke 22. 41. <hi>It's ſaid Jeſus kneeled down and prayed.</hi> Acts 7. 60. Stephen <hi>kneeled down and pray'd for his murtherers,</hi> Peter <hi>in like manner,</hi> Act 9. 40. <hi>kneeled down and pray'd for</hi> Dorcas, Paul <hi>alſo,</hi> as it's ſaid, Acts 20. 36. <hi>kneeled down and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Diſciples at</hi> Miletus: and not only <hi>Paul</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but the Congregation of the Diſciples, that were with him at <hi>Tyre,</hi> upon the taking leave of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>kneeled down on the ſhore and pray'd.</hi> Act 21. 5.</p>
            <p>Now can it be ſuppoſed that our Saviour and his diſciples did not underſtand the will of the Lord in this matter, as well as any of us do now adays, or ſhall we pretend to a more pure and ſpiritual way of worſhipping God, than they did; ſince therefore they thought fit to practice outward reverence in prayer, let us walk by the ſame rule and follow their example, And then as to keeping off your Hat all the time that the Miniſter is preaching and expounding unto you the word of God, this alſo you muſt be careful to obſerve and do.</p>
            <p>For ſtill you ſhould ſuppoſe your ſelf to be in God's more eſpecial preſence, as well while his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador is expounding unto you the Scripture, as while he is offering up his prayers to God in your behalf. If therefore you are not able, through ſome natural infirmity, to be bare-headed all the time of Divine Service and Sermon, you may then make uſe of a decent Cap; for tho the Head be partly cover'd with that, yet it being not ſuch a common covering as your Hat, but ſuch a one as is accounted to be conſiſtent with reverence among men, therefore it is no diſhonour to God, for he expects to be reverenc'd by us in thoſe ways, by which we reverence one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>As therefore we would not preſume to go and ſit down in the preſence of an earthly King, when we petition his Majeſty for ſome favour to be granted us, nor confidently put on our Hats while he ſpeaks un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57468:18"/> us, but would behave our ſelves with that humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and reverence which is uſual in thoſe caſes, ſo neither ſhould we preſume to behave our ſelves irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and proudly in Gods preſence.</p>
            <p>But beſides, ſuch irreverence is to be avoided, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the great ſcandal which is thereby given to thoſe of the Congregation, who are truly devout, for ſo St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches us, 1 Cor. 10. 32. <hi>that we ſhould give no offence, neither to the Jew nor to the Gentiles nor to the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, it is to be conſider'd that ſuch irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is a very great piece of injuſtice, a robbing God of that honour which is due unto him, for as he made, and doth preſerve, not only the Heart but the outward members, as the Hands, Eyes, Tongue and the whole man, ſo all of them ſhould concur in, rendring their tribute of reverence and ſervice to him.</p>
            <p>And thus having ſhewed you the neceſſity of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rencing God, both outwardly in your Body, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in your Soul, you may from hence learn to avoid the two dangerous extreams, of profaneneſs and ſuperſtition, and neither be diſcouraged from the practice of outward reverence, by thoſe who ſhall cenſure you for being formal, nor incouraged to the neglect of inward reverence by thoſe who place the whole of their religion in an outward ſhew.</p>
            <p>And therefore, as I ſaid at firſt, be perſwaded at all times when you go to the Houſe of God to conſider with your ſelf before hand what you are going about, and compoſe your thoughts in ſuch a manner, as that you may behave your ſelf all the time of prayer, and other parts of Religious Worſhip with all ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and gravity, as in the preſence of an All-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infinitely pure and glorious God.</p>
            <p>And now becauſe I am ſenſible that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who are guilty of ſome miſtakes in expreſſing their reverence in publick Worſhip according to the rules of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> through want of a right information in the matter, to prevent your being alſo guilty of the like, I ſhall here take occaſion to let
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57468:18"/> you know wherein one or two of their miſtakes do lye.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place therefore, it is very uſual with many who kneel at the <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> to ſtand up or ſit down at the <hi>Abſolution.</hi> And perhaps the reaſon of their ſtanding up is, becauſe they obſerve the Miniſter does ſo.</p>
            <p>Whereas you muſt know, that there is not the ſame reaſon for the one, which there is for the other; for as to the Miniſters ſtanding up at the <hi>Abſolution,</hi> this is done to ſignify that Authority, by which he pronounces to thoſe who are truly penitent, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and remiſſion of their ſins, it being more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that all Miniſterial acts of Authority ſhould be done ſtanding; but at the ſame time it is fit that the whole Congregation ſhould continue kneeling as at their <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> and behave themſelves in the humble poſture of Penitents, while with the moſt ſubmiſſive attention, they hear Gods Gracious Declaration of pardon, pronounc'd unto them by the mouth of his Miniſter.</p>
            <p>In the next place it is alſo uſual with many to ſtand up at the <hi>Communion Service,</hi> or at leaſt ſo ſoon as the Miniſter begins to read the ten Commandments; and this it's probable they uſe to do, becauſe they obſerve the Miniſter then ſtanding up; but as I ſaid before, ſo here again it is to be conſider'd, that there is not the ſame reaſon for both; the Miniſter ſtands up becauſe it is the moſt proper geſture for him, while he declare the Law of God unto the people; but at the ſame time it is moſt proper for the Congregation to kneel, becauſe at the concluſion of every Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, they are to pray to God for the pardon of their former tranſgreſſinos, and for Grace not to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs again, ſaying <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, and incline our hearts to keep this law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That you may not therefore follow the example of others, who are either ignorant or careleſs in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you may do well to ask your own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whether there be any of the ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which you have not broken either in thought,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57468:19"/> word or deed, and whether you are not ſtill in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of tranſgreſſing the ſame, and then ſay whether you have not need with all humility both of Soul and Body, to pray unto the Lord for mercy and for grace in that pious Ejaculation, which the Church has directed, ſaying <hi>Lord have mercy, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now after all, tho it highly concern you (as I have ſhewed) ſo to behave your ſelf in the publick worſhip of God, that you may offer up to him ſuch a reaſonable ſervice, as he will be pleaſed to accept of through the merits and meditation of his beloved Son, yet I muſt withal tell you that you muſt have a care of limiting your devotion to the Temple, you muſt not think it enough to ſeem very ſerious there, if at other times you be vain and wicked.</p>
            <p>If you deſire that both your perſon and your perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances ſhould be accepted of God, you muſt be truly religious at all times, and the zeal which you pretend to have for Gods glory muſt be viſible through the whole courſe of your life and converſation.</p>
            <p>Be perſwaded therefore to remember your Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the days of your youth, have a care of thinking (as too many do) that you have ſtill time enough to prepare your ſelf for another world, for there's no man knows how ſoon the great Judge of Heaven and Earth may call him hence.</p>
            <p>It is certainly the greateſt piece of ill husbandry that you can be guilty of, to think that you can eaſily redeem that time when you pleaſe, which you ſhall mortgage for a few vain and inſatisfactory de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
            <p>There are too many I doubt in the world that flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves, and think that they go upon good grounds, while they defer to give up themſelves to Gods ſervice in the vigour of their youth, hoping that they may repent when they ſee their own time.</p>
            <p>But (my Son) I beſeech you to conſider, that altho God has promiſed pardon to all the true penitents, yet he has not particularly promiſed to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it on any mans leiſure.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57468:19"/>
            <p> He does indeed bear with ſome a long time, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their converſion, and ſuch is his infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he does ſometime grant repentance and pardon after men have for many years put off that neceſſary duty, but he never does this upon any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contract with them, nor does any thing more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke him to deny his favours, than mens preſuming thus to diſpoſe of them.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe I ſhall offer unto your conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a remarkable paſſage, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 33. where we find that the Lord forbore King <hi>Manaſſes</hi> forty years, and at length upon his repentance pardon'd him: After his death <hi>Amon</hi> his Son reigned in his ſtead, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obſerved, it's like, how merciful God had dealt with his Father, he preſumed upon the like forbearance and mercy, thinking that as his Father had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo he might redeem the offences of his youth by a late repentance in old age; but we find that God was not pleaſed to accept of <hi>Amon</hi>'s aſſignment, and therefore tho he had ſpared <hi>Manaſſes</hi> the Father forty years, yet he cut off his Son at the end of the ſecond year of his wicked Reign.</p>
            <p>Know therefore and conſider this, that it is good for you to bear the yoke of Religion in your youth; if you habituate your ſelf to the practice of holineſs in the prime of your years, you will afterwards find all, even the ſevereſt Duties of Chriſtianity, to ſit wonderful eaſie upon your mind, if you ſhould live to be old.</p>
            <p>You'll then have nothing of that regret and anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to diſcompoſe your thoughts, which others will feel who have neglected the ſervice of God in their youth, and enſlaved themſelves to the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil.</p>
            <p>It is obſervable that <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt is called the diſciple whom Jeſus loved; it is not ſaid indeed for what reaſon this Title was given him above all the reſt of the Twelve Apoſtles, but it being ſuppoſed that he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he youngeſt of them all, for that reaſon poſſibly Jeſus might have the greater love for him, becauſe even then in the days of his youth, he had
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57468:20"/> learned to deſpiſe all the bewitching vanities of the world, to deny himſelf, and heartily to embrace the Doctrine of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>If therefore (my Son) this advice which I have here given you, may through the Grace of God prove beneficial to you, and anſwer the end for which it is deſigned, in furthering the Salvation of your Soul, I ſhall be heartily glad, and hope, that both you and I ſhall aſcribe the whole Praiſe and Glory to God.</p>
            <div type="appendix">
               <head>An Appendix, touching Baptiſmal Sureties.</head>
               <p>BEing very ſenſible, that there is ſeldom any thing which occaſions greater diſputes and differences between many Miniſters and their Pariſhioners, than the buſineſs of Baptiſmal Sureties, and that nothing is more commonly pretended by ſome for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their departing from our Church, than their being diſſatisfied about this matter, I have here thought fit to add ſomething in reference hereunto, hoping thereby to remove the ſcruples, at leaſt, of thoſe who are unprejudic'd and well meaning per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>In order to this end I ſhall ſhow you,
<list>
                     <item>1ſt. What is meant by God-fathers and God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</item>
                     <item>2d. What reaſon our Church has to juſtifie the uſe of them.</item>
                     <item>3d. How advantageous the due execution of this Office may be both to Sureties and Children.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, as to the meaning of God-fathers and God-mothers, our Church hereby underſtands thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are engaged as Sureties to the Church by ſolemn promiſe at the Baptiſm of Children, to ſee them virtuouſly brought up, to lead a Godly and a Chriſtian Life.</p>
               <p>So that altho the Chriſtian Church for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t reaſon has thought fit to call them Sureties, yet to let them know, how they ought to be affected toward their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57468:20"/> Children, in whoſe names they covenant with God, <hi>viz.</hi> that they ought to be as Fathers and Mothers in God, <hi>i e.</hi> ſpiritual parents. And affectionately concerned in the furtherance of their Childrens Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, therefore they are called God-fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this way of expreſſing themſelves in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we may ſuppoſe the ancient Chriſtians at firſt received from ſome expreſſions in Scripture of the like nature, as when all true believers are ſaid to be brethren in Chriſt, and therefore are called Chriſtians, as alſo from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s way of ſpeaking concerning thoſe perſons, in whoſe education, and in the furtherance of whoſe Salvation he had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
               <p>For as he ſignifies to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 4. 15. that he was their ſpiritual Father, <hi>having begotten them in Chriſt Jeſus through the Goſpel;</hi> ſo 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>he calls Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy his own Son in the Faith.</hi> In this ſenſe alſo he calls <hi>Oneſimus</hi> his Son, <hi>Ep to Philem. v.</hi> 10. <hi>I beſeech thee for my Son Oneſimus, whom I have begotten in my bounds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as St <hi>Paul</hi> was father to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and as <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Oneſimus</hi> were his Sons, in a Spiritual ſenſe, ſo why may not thoſe perſons who undertake the office of Sureties for Children, when they bring them to Baptiſm, which is their new and ſpiritual Birth, be called ſpiritual Parents, or God-fathers and God-mothers, eſpecially when they are as they ought to be, and as they may be, ſpiritually affected toward their Children.</p>
               <p>And how far ſoever many are now a days from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, it's not to be doubted but that they were much more tenderly affected toward them in antient times.</p>
               <p>For names are uſually given at firſt according to the nature of things, and therefore it is not reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that any of us ſhould be ſo averſe both to the name and the office, becauſe ſome are ſo very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in the performance of what they do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take.</p>
               <p>It is our duty rather conſcientiouſly to undertake and diſcharge this office (which we may do if we
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57468:21"/> will) to the glory of God, the ſpiritual advantage of one anothers Children, and the comfort of our own Souls.</p>
               <p>Let no one therefore deceive you, and make you believe, that there is any thing of Popiſh ſuperſtition in the uſe of Sureties, for it is certain from the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Hiſtories of the Church, that there were God-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Chriſtian Church, many years before there was any ſuch thing as Popery known in the world.</p>
               <p>And ſuch Sureties are at this day retained not only here in <hi>England,</hi> but in thoſe Churches beyond the Seas, who never did embrace the Popiſh Religion.</p>
               <p>Thus having ſhew'd you what is meant by God-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall in the</p>
               <p>2d place ſhow you what reaſon our Church has to juſtifie the uſe of them; for it being matter only of Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, I do not ſuppoſe that there is any neceſſity of an expreſs command, or example in Scripture for it.</p>
               <p>It may ſuffice us therefore, that it be go runded upon good reaſon, and ſo I ſuppoſe it is.</p>
               <p>For if we will allow, that Children ſhould be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, (as we very well may, and not doubt but that God will alſo allow the ſame) we muſt by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence allow them the benefit of having others to Covenant with God for them, and who may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged afterward to ſee them inſtructed in the principles of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>And that it's no new or impoſſible thing for Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to covenant with God by others, we may learn from <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 10, 11, 12. for there we find that not only the elder Perſons, who could underſtand and ſpeak for themſelves, but even their little ones were brought to covenant with God, which they could not do but by others, and yet thoſe Children were as much obliged to ſtand to that Covenant, as the elder perſons who were of age and underſtanding to Covenant for themſelves; as appears by thoſe and the following verſes in the fore-mentioned Ch. of <hi>Deut.</hi> Beſides, this is no more than what is daily
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57468:21"/> practic'd in behalf of Children in worldly matters, for when Parents dye, and leave Eſtates and Portions for their young Children, they leave ſome Friends in truſt with them; and theſe perſons contract and make bargains in their names, and if thoſe be fair and advantageous, the Children, in whoſe names they are made, are obliged to ſtand to them, and make them good when they come of age.</p>
               <p>And that we have no reaſon to doubt of God's ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the Faith of Sureties in behalf of Children, may appear not only from Gods acceptance of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Faith for circumciſing his Son, but from Chriſts ready acceptance of the <hi>woman of Canaans faith for the cure of her Daughter,</hi> Mat. 15. 22. as alſo <hi>from his accepting the charitable intention of thoſe that brought the man ſick of the Palſey to be cured by him,</hi> Mark 2. 5. Thus having ſhew'd you that the Churches uſe of Baptiſmal Sureties is grounded upon good reaſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore has been ſo long approved of through all parts of the world where the Goſpel has been preacht, from the Apoſtles times, or very near them, to this day, one would think there ſhould not be ſo much diſpute among Chriſtians about this matter; but becauſe there are many Objections made againſt this order of our Church, therefore I ſhall now proceed to give as ſatisfactory anſwers as I can to thoſe Objections which I have met with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. Therefore, ſay ſome, we find no ſuch thing commanded in Scripture, as God-fathers and God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, nor example of any ſuch matter, nor ſo much as any ſuch words therein mentioned, and therefore we cannot think fit to make uſe of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer whereunto it is to be conſidered that God has no where in his holy word ty'd us up ſo ſtrictly in matters of Church diſcipline, that we muſt do nothing but juſt what is expreſly command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or what we have an example for; for what Sect of Chriſtians is there who do not for love and orders ſake, obſerve ſome things for which they have neither a particular precept no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> example.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:57468:22"/>
               <p> It may be ſufficient that ſuch things are agreeable to the general rule of the Apoſtle, 1. Cor. 14. 40. <hi>that all things be done decently and in order, and tending to edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> v. 26. This rule ſuppoſes that the particular matters of Church Diſcipline ſhould be left to Church Governours, and to the cuſtom of the Church, not contrary to the rule of Scripture, and no way deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the Glory of God.</p>
               <p>So that this having been the conſtant cuſtom of the Church, in the pureſt times of the Goſpel after the Apoſtles days, to require Sureties for Children at their Baptiſm, why may not the Churches cuſtom juſtifie our practice? eſpecially in this caſe, wherein there is nothing of indecency but what may very much tend to edification and the Glory of God, if it be rightly obſerv'd.</p>
               <p>As to your finding no mention made of the words in Scripture, that's no argument againſt the things; for neither do we find the word <hi>Trinity,</hi> nor the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> in Scripture, and yet we think fit to make uſe of thoſe words, the one being moſt proper to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the three perſons in the Godhead, and the other to ſignify the two great ordinances of the Goſpel, <hi>viz.</hi> Baptiſm and the Lords Supper. But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not good (ſay ſome) to undertake this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, nor to deſire others to do it, becauſe there are none that diſcharge their duty in this matter.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, that ſome have diſcharged their duty is moſt certain, and I could give you ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to prove, that to the pious care of Baptiſmal Sureties in inſtructing ſome of your Royal Princes in the Principles of ſound Religion, we owe in a great meaſure the enjoyment of the Proteſtant Religion in this Nation. And that all others do not diſcharge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir duty, is not becauſe there is any impoſſibility in the nature of the thing; for cannot any of us uſe our beſt endeavours to ſee that a Child be taught ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oon as he ſhall be able to learn what a ſolemn Vow, Promiſe and Profeſſion he has made by his Sureties? cannot they take care that he may learn the Church Catechiſm, which contains in it all the fundamental
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57468:22"/> truths which a Chriſtian ought to know and believe to his Souls health? cannot they call upon him to hear Sermons, unleſs they happen to be removed at too great a diſtance from each other? and finally, cannot they do what in them lies to have him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, and ſo to diſcharge them by taking the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon himſelf?</p>
               <p>Surely there is nothing of impoſſibility in any of theſe things, and yet theſe are the chief things that are given in charge to the Sureties. But</p>
               <p n="3">3. Say ſome, why ſhould not the Parents rather than others be obliged to undertake theſe things?</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, that Parents are already obliged both by the Law of God and Nature, to take care of their Children's Souls and Bodies, and there can be no greater obligation laid upon them, by requiring a ſolemn promiſe from them.</p>
               <p>And therefore, as a Reverend and Learned Biſhop of our Church obſerves, <q>The Churches intention in having Sureties, is not to ſupercede the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Parents, but to ſuperinduce a farther obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon others for greater ſecurity of performance. Or, as another has expreſs'd it, the Church thinks fit to lay the charge upon others, not to exclude or excuſe the Parents care, but to be joyned with them in the more certain and eaſie accompliſhment of ſo pious a work.</q> But,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Say ſome, how can Sureties declare in the Childs name, that he does renounce the Devil and all his works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that he does believe in God, or how can they promiſe that the Child ſhall ſerve him, ſince we find it ſo hard a matter to do theſe things our ſelves.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer in the firſt place, that theſe words of the Baptiſmal Vow are not directly words of promiſe, obliging the Sureties to performance, but expreſſions of contract relating to the Infant, and declaring to what Duties he is obliged by his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, which are no other than what every one of us ought to do (as I have already ſhew'd) who expects to be ſav'd.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57468:23"/>
               <p> In the ſecond place, it is indeed more than we know, whether the child when he comes to years of diſcretion, will perform thoſe things which at his Baptiſm were promiſed in his name.</p>
               <p>But then, does not the ſame objection lye againſt thoſe who oppoſe us in this matter; for is it not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as uncertain, whether thoſe Parents, who (as they are enjoyned by the Presbyterian Directory) ſhall ſolemnly promiſe to bring up their Children in the grounds of the Chriſtian Religion, and in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, ſhall be able to do it, who knows whether the incapacity or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſs and obſtinacy of the Child, (admitting that the Parents were careful in the matter) may not hinder the performance of their promiſe?</p>
               <p>Yea, is it not altogether as uncertain whether thoſe perſons who are not dipt till they come to ripeneſs of years, will conſcientiouſly obſerve and keep the Covenant which they make then with God after their way? And yet notwithſtanding this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty on all hands, 'tis fit all parties ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe thoſe things which it is their duty to perform.</p>
               <p>However, we have the greater encouragement to hope for the Child's well-doing, becauſe as the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church are put up unto God in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, that he may have power and ſtrength to have victory, and to triumph againſt the Devil, the World and the Fleſh, ſo we have Gods promiſe, that he will grant thoſe things which we ask faithfully at his hands.</p>
               <p>And therefore, by the way, this conſideration ſhould oblige all people who were preſent at the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Baptiſm, to put up their hearty prayers to God in behalf of thoſe who are baptized, and not to ſit down or ſtand gazing about, as if they were no way concern'd therein.</p>
               <p>The Prayers of the Church therefore being put up to God in the Childs behalf, and God having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to hear our prayers, if afterward the Sureties take care (as they may do if they will) when the Child is come to years of diſcretion, to let him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57468:23"/> know what they had promiſed for him, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him the beſt they can to be mindful thereof, they have done their duty, and they may reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly expect the bleſſing of God upon their endeavours. But,</p>
               <p n="5">5. Say ſome, why ſhould any perſons be deſired to take this charge upon them, ſince it very often falls out, that either the Sureties are removed at a great diſtance from the Children, or the Children from them, before they are capable of being inſtructed as they ſhould be, ſo that the duty cannot poſſibly be diſcharged according to promiſe.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, that it is very certain theſe things may, and do happen very often, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Parents would do well, to make choice of ſuch Sureties as are Inhabitants, and not Strangers or Servants, and ſuch as have no ſettled place of abode, unleſs they are known to be perſons religiouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, who may take care, tho they live at ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, to diſcharge their duty.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſing that the circumſtances of either party ſhould be ſuch, that there is an unavoidable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of removing from one another, and that the thing cannot be done ſo well as if they continued ſtill in the ſame neighbourhood, the Sureties are in ſuch a caſe diſcharged from ſo much of their duty, as they cannot poſſibly perform. But then they ſhould be mindful of ſuch Children in their private devotions, beſeeching God to direct them by his holy Spirit, in the ways of truth and righteouſneſs, and to grant unto them minds capable of receiving ſuch good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction as may be tender'd unto them; that if he would ſeaſon their hearts with grace, and that he ſhall pleaſed to prolong their days here upon earth, they may live to him, and be inſtruments of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by ſerving him faithfully, and doing good in their generation.</p>
               <p>This ſuppoſition therefore of a removal on either ſide, is of no more force againſt Sureties, than that of their death, which may happen in a little time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Child is baptized, for in all ſuch caſes of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57468:24"/> we ought to do our duty, and leave the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue to the all-wiſe diſpoſer of all things.</p>
               <p>Thus we act in leaving our Children to Guardians, who are to take care of their wordly concerns, and why ſhall not we truſt providence in the other caſes as well as this.</p>
               <p>And now having ſhow'd you the reaſonableneſs of our Churches practice in requiring Baptiſmal Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and having anſwered thoſe objections, which I have heard made againſt it, I ſhall add but one argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more, which yet ought to be of great weight with us in ſuch like caſes, and that's the neceſſity of every Chriſtians ſubmitting to all the Lawful orders of that Church, whereof he is a member. For ſo S. <hi>Peter</hi> teaches 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>ſubmitting your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here you ſee we are in conſcience obliged to be obedient to our Governours in all thoſe things which they may lawfully require us to do, and not only to the civil Magiſtrate, but alſo to the Church Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, for ſo St <hi>Paul</hi> has taught us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. <hi>Obey them that have the rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls, as they, that muſt give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that they may do it with joy, and not with grief, for that is unprofitable for you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that there is no unlawfulneſs in the uſe of Sureties, I have ſhow'd already, and conſequently theſe general rules of the Apoſtle ſhould oblige us to yield obedience in this caſe.</p>
               <p>It being therefore expreſly required in the 29th Canon of our Church, that no Parent ſhould be urg'd to be preſent, nor admitted to anſwer as God-father to his own Child, and that there ſhould be for every male Child two God-fathers and one God-mother, and for every female two God-mothers and one God-father.</p>
               <p>And that no perſon ſhould be admitted God-father or God-mother, before the ſaid perſon hath received the Holy Communion; it is to be wiſhed, that all who profeſs themſelves Members of our Church, would behave themſelves more regularly in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57468:24"/> than generally they do, and not contradict the general rule of the Goſpel, by acting contrary to this particular order of the Church; which if duly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, would be of very great advantage both to Sureties and Children upon ſeveral accounts, as I ſhall now in the third place proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to ſhow you.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For to be Surety for a Child is a very Chriſtian and charitable work; if it be an act of great charity to take pity upon a poor forlorn infant, who is almoſt naked and ready to be ſtarved for want of food, how much better is it to be inſtrumental in deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Soul from death, as Sureties may be through the bleſſing of God, upon their ſincere endeavour thro the merits of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Beſides, a Surety by furthering the Childs Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may bring com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort unto his own Soul: for you know if a man do but plant a young Tree, and by taking great care of it, finds it thrive and proſper, he ſeems to take ſome delight and pleaſure in it; but how much greater is a Chriſtians comfort, when by Gods bleſſing upon thoſe good inſtructions and exhortations, which according to his promiſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows upon a Child, he finds the Child grow in Grace, and Godlineſs, and Spiritual Strength, and bringing forth the Fruits of Holineſs and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
               <p>Finally, by this means every one of us may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderably advance the Intereſt of Religion, and give a check to the prevailing wickedneſs, and great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries of the Age we live in.</p>
               <p>If it ſhall pleaſe God therefore (my Son) to give you the great bleſſing of Children, let not their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm be neglected, but ſee they be dedicated unto the Lord by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rding to the Directions of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt or ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon ſome Holiday fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ublick prayer in the Church.</p>
               <p>And be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u take the beſt care you can to provide ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> may make conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57468:25"/> of diſcharging their duty; and if when you are capable of undertaking that office your ſelf, any one ſhall deſire the like kindneſs of you, ſee that you readily comply with their requeſt, reſolving with your ſelf to contribute all you can toward promoting the Glory of God, and the peace of Chriſt's Holy Church; and in carrying on that great work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, which is now adays ſo very needful in the world.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>BOOKS <hi>printed for</hi> James Knap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, <hi>at the</hi> Crown <hi>in</hi> St Paul<hi>'s</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <p>DIſcourſes on the Revenues, and on the Trade of <hi>England,</hi> in 2 parts.</p>
            <p>An Eſſay on the Ballance of Trade.</p>
            <p>Diſcourſes on Grants and Reſumptions. Theſe 4 by the Author of the Eſſays on Ways and Means.</p>
            <p>Captain <hi>Wm. Dampiers</hi> Voyages, 2 vol. 8vo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wafers</hi> Voyages in 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Malbranch</hi> Treatiſe of Moralit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, 8<hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hacks</hi> Collection of Voyages, 8vo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>arks</hi> Eſſays, 8vo.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:57468:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
